Finding Aid for Don't Waste Michigan records, 1987-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Don't Waste Michigan records 1987-1990
Don't Waste Michigan.
0.5 linear feet.
91458 Bn 2
Citizen group opposed to the placement of a regional low-level radioactive waste disposal facility in Michigan. Administrative files include minutes and agenda of meetings, newsletters, press releases and promotional flyers, and brief history; background information on proposed superconducting super collider.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by Eunice Hendrix (Donor No. 7858 ) in November, 1990.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Don't Waste Michigan (DWM) is a citizen's group originally formed in March, 1988 to oppose the placement of a regional radioactive waste disposal facility in Michigan. The group also called for the withdrawal of Michigan from the Midwest Interstate Compact, a seven state coalition to develop a regional low level radioactive waste disposal site.
In 1989, Don't Waste Michigan filed a law suit to force the Low Level Radioactive Waste Authority to disclose the sites that were to be considered for a radioactive waste dump in Michigan. They won that suit in September of 1989. The group's most recent concerns include (1) resisting efforts to weaken the waste dump selection criteria, (2) passing a law banning "below regulatory concern radioactive wastes" from Michigan landfills and waterways, (3) resisting an effort to privatize the selection process which would eliminate public participation in site selection, and (4) Superconducting Super Collider (SSC) opposition.
The Central Steering Committee for Don't Waste Michigan tried to provide leadership for local DWM organizations in the areas of education, membership, funding, publications, legal issues, chapter coordination, and media relations. Members of the Steering Committee as of March, 1988 included Mary Sinclair, Midland, Education and Media; Ellen Beal, Lansing, Membership and Newsletter; Corrine Carey, Grand Rapids, Publications; Eunice Hendrix, Ann Arbor, Fundraising and Treasurer; Chuck Will, Lansing, Legal Research; Nancy Fagge, Warren, Chapter Coordinator; and Brian Ewart, Ann Arbor, Strategy and Meeting Coordinator.
The Don't Waste Michigan record group is comprised of materials collected by one of the members of the 1988 Central Steering Committee, Eunice Hendrix of Ann Arbor, Michigan. The record group cover the period of 1987 to 1990 and is divided into two series: Administrative Files and Background Files on Superconducting Super Collider.
Subjects:
Citizens' associations--Michigan.; Don't Waste Michigan.; Environmental protection--Michigan.; Radioactive waste disposal--Michigan.; Superconducting Super Collider.
- Administrative File, 1987-1990
  The Administrative File series documents DWM's work against the proposed low-level radioactive waste dump proposed for placement in Michigan. The Administrative File reveals the month to month workings of a grassroots coalition. These folders contain the richest source of information on the motivation behind the Don't Waste Michigan campaigns.
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
  - By-Laws, 1987 (Box 1)
  - History of Don't Waste Michigan, ca. 1990 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
  - Press Releases and Promotional Flyers, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
- Background File on the Superconducting Super Collider (Ssc)
  The second series, Background Files on SSC, consists of background information on the proposed location of the SSC in Michigan. There is not a strong link between the discussions in the Administrative File series and the SSC background series files. The Department of Energy subseries and the Local/Regional Information subseries both contain material that federal and state agencies published in support of the SSC. The Topical File subseries contains material from the press and journals discussing various issues regarding the proposed SSC.
  - Department of Energy (DOE) Information on the SSC
    - Draft Environmental Impact Statement (DEIS), Superconducting Super Collider. Volumes I and III, Volume IV-Appendix 4, DOE/EIS-0138D, U.S. Dept. of Energy, August 1988 (printed material) (Box 1)
    - Federal Register Notice for DEIS, January 22, 1988 (Box 1)
    - SSC Central Design Group Publications on Radiation and the SSC, July and November, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Waste Generation at the SSC; Background Information, August, 19 (Box 1)
  - Local/Regional Information and Publications on the SSC
    - Institute for Social Research, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Public Hearing Texts; Questions and Statements Regarding the DEIS and the SSC in Michigan, September 1988 and ca. 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - State of Michigan, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Topical Files
    - Editorials, 1987 and undated (Box 1)
    - Journal Articles, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
    - SSC Buttons and Bumper Sticker (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)